Guide to the John Randolph Papers WAG.255
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
John Randolph Papers
1918-1999
1940-1999
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Randolph, John, 1915-2004
Randolph, Martha
WAG.255
8 Linear Feet in 8 record cartons and 1 oversized folder
1 videocassette
31 audiocassette on 23 open reels and 8 cassette tapes
1 dvd-r disks
Born Emanuel Hirsch Cohen in the Bronx, New York on June 1, 1915, Randolph was renamed Mortimer Lippman at the age of 12 when his mother remarried, and finally emerged as the actor, John Randolph. He began his acting career in the 1930s with the Federal Theatre Project. His first Broadway role came courtesy of the Project when he appeared in Coriolanus in 1938. His final Broadway appearance was as a replacement for the lead in Prelude to a Kiss in 1991. He won the prestigious Tony Award for his performance in Neil Simon's Broadway Bound. In January 1942, while on the road with a production of Native Son starring Canada Lee, John married actress Sarah Cunningham of Greenville, South Carolina, Shortly thereafter he was drafted into the Army Air Corps where he served for the next four years. Television found Randolph in 1948 and lost him in 1951 when he was blacklisted. During the blacklist period he continued to work in theatre and developed new performance opportunities with his fellow blacklistees' actress Phoebe Brand, educator Frederic Ewen, and his wife, Sarah. In August of 1955 John and Sarah both appeared before the House Committee on Un-American Activities (HUAC) where they both invoked the Fifth Amendment. Randolph's television career began to revive slowly in the early 1960s. His film career got off to a strong start in 1966, when he played a banker who undergoes surgery and awakens as Rock Hudson in John Frankenheimer's Seconds. He made his final film appearance in 2003. A champion of civil rights, a fighter for more opportunities for performers of color, a lifelong supporter of progressive causes, John Randolph, actor and activist, was silenced by death in Los Angeles, California on February 24, 2004. The collection consists of Randolph's personal and professional files, reflecting his passions for acting, activism, social justice and his intense relationship with his wife, Sarah Cunningham. The materials range from their correspondence during World War II, to opening night telegrams for various Broadway productions, to performance pieces used during the blacklist period and Randolph's Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) file.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by John Randolph's daughter, Martha Randolph, in June 2004. The accession number associated with this gift is 2004.032.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically within each series. Organized into 4 series: I, Correspondence, 1918-1999; II, Subject Files, 1940-1999; III, Productions and Professional Activities, 1938-1999; IV, Oversize Materials, 1955.
Historical/Biographical Note
John Randolph the actor, as he would always introduce himself, was born Emanuel Hirsch Cohen in the Bronx, New York on June 1, 1915. He was renamed Mortimer Lippman at the age of 12 when his mother remarried, and finally emerged as John Randolph when he began his acting career in the 1930s with the Federal Theatre Project. His first Broadway role came courtesy of the Project when he appeared in Coriolanus in 1938. He received his formal theatre training from the Dramatic Workshop of the New School for Social Research under the director of Erwin Piscator. He appeared on Broadway four more times before going on the road with a production of Native Son starring Canada Lee in 1941. It was during this tour that Randolph had a number of opportunities to demonstrate his strong sensitivity to civil rights.
1941 proved to be a very important year in Randolph's life. On June 22, 1941, as Germany marched into Russia, John came together with a young actress from Greenville, South Carolina: Sarah Cunningham who shared with him not only a passion for acting but for activism as well. It was their acting careers that kept them apart for most of the rest of 1941. On a visit during the run of Native Son, the pair decided to marry. They wed at high noon on Wednesday, January 6, 1942, prior to John's matinee. Hours later Sarah was on her way to back to New York. In April John (as Mortimer Lippman again) was drafted into the Army Air Corps where he served for the next four years.
By 1948 Randolph was again back on Broadway. Also in 1948, television found him, but just as his television career was beginning to gain momentum in 1951, he was blacklisted. During the blacklist period he considered himself lucky as he was able to continue working in theatre. With the wealth of energy that defined him in the years to come he developed new performance opportunities with his fellow blacklistees, actress Phoebe Brand, educator Frederic Ewen, and his wife, Sarah. They appeared in union halls and Jewish community centers in between theatre engagements. In August of 1955, John and Sarah both appeared before the House Committee on Un-American Activities (HUAC). They both invoked their rights under the Fifth Amendment. After his HUAC appearance, John got back on the train and returned to his engagement at the Brattle Summer Theatre in Cambridge, Massachusetts.
As the blacklist period started to fade, in the early 1960s, Randolph's television career began to revive slowly. By this time he was serving on the Council of Actors' Equity and heavily involved with the American Federation of Television and Radio Actors, organizations with which he would remain active for the rest of his life. His film career finally got off to a strong start in 1966, when he played a banker who undergoes surgery and awakens as Rock Hudson in John Frankenheimer's Seconds. Having the good fortune of being a proficient character actor, Randolph never stopped working. One of his more notable performances was as Angelo 'Pop' Partanna in the 1985 film, Prizzi's Honor. When the film was nominated for the Academy Award as Best Picture, John and Sarah were invited to join the company at the ceremony. During the evening, Sarah excused herself and went to the ladies room; it was there that she died of a heart attack.
For the remainder of his life, Randolph continued working. In 1986, he began a long and successful run in Neil Simon's Broadway Bound, in a part tailor-made for him. John won the prestigious Tony Award for this performance. His final Broadway appearance was as a replacement for the lead in Prelude to a Kiss in 1991. He continued to work in theatre outside of Broadway, as well as in television and film, making his final appearance in film in 2003.
No biography of Randolph and Cunningham would be complete without recognizing the depth of their activism. Their passion for each other was matched only by their passion for the causes they held dear. Champions of civil rights, fighters for more opportunities for performers of color, and voices for the power of the industry that clothed and fed them throughout their lives, they were lifelong supporters of progressive causes. John Randolph, actor and activist, died in Los Angeles on February 24, 2004.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Records of the Actors Equity Association. (Wagner #11)
Records of the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists. (Wagner #281)
Records of the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists-New York Local. (Wagner #282)
Frederic Ewen Oral History Collection. (OH #52)
Frederic Ewen Papers. (Tamiment #277)
Scope and Content Note
The John Randolph papers consist of his personal and professional files. They reflect his passions for acting, activism, social justice and his intense relationship with his wife, Sarah Cunningham. The materials range from a very personal, but still political, correspondence with his new wife during the years of World War II to notes sent backstage when he was appearing in Broadway Bound; from his Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) file to the work he created to keep him and his fellow blacklistees employed. The papers are organized into three series.
Series I: Correspondence, 1918-1999. Over the years John wrote, and received, letters that ranged from the political to the personal, and often both. This series includes correspondence from around the world; notable are the letters between Randolph and Sarah Cunningham during the years of World War II. The letters begin on July 8, 1941, when each writes a letter to the other. The correspondence carries on through John's (now Mortimer again as far as the army is concerned) service in the Army Air Corps, which begins in April of 1942 and ends in December 1945. Other incoming correspondence includes letters from film and theatre notables such as Jules Dassin and Frank Silvera.
Series II: Subject Files, 1940-1999, contains files illustrating Randolph's political concerns, including the Committee for Employment of Negro Performers and the New York State Commission for Human Rights. As a member and then councilor at Actors' Equity, he was active in the ethnic minorities and Paul Robeson Award committees. His strong involvement with the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists (AFTRA) is seen in files on the blacklist and on the House Committee on Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC). Material from this period includes clippings from before, during and after his Committee appearance in 1955, as well as related correspondence and his FOIA file. His later involvement in the Screen Actors Guild (SAG) is also chronicled. Other issues represented include freedom for Angela Davis, international friendship societies, Vietnam, women's rights, and the Rosenberg Case.
Series III: Productions and Professional Activities, 1938-1999, contains documentation of most productions Randolph appeared in, from The Living Flame in 1939 to the original Broadway productions of Come Back Little Sheba (1950), Paint Your Wagon (1951), Sound of Music (1959), and his Tony Award-winning turn in Broadway Bound (1986). Theatre files also include Off-Broadway, summer stock and road companies (besides Native Son mentioned earlier, he appeared with Melvyn Douglas in Inherit the Wind), and there are files on his radio, television, and film work. From the early days of the blacklist onward Randolph gathered material that could be used in concert readings, and saved the notes he had compiled for his work. He excerpted plays, film scripts, stories, and adapted material with the help of Phoebe Brand and Frederic Ewen. Their appearances were often under the banner of Quartette Productions. Also included are scripts for a number of benefit performances. Randolph produced for Stage for Action's Satire Matinee, presented in 1946 at Café Society; was artistic consultant for the Philadelphia Drama Guild, and, with Sarah Cunningham, helped found the Ensemble Studio Theatre in both New York and Los Angeles.
Series IV: Oversize Material, 1955: contains a scrapbook of clippings and statements re: the 1955 HUAC hearings compiled for a benefit on June 12, 1997 at the Stella Adler Studio in Los Angeles, California, and an ad from Variety dated July 27, 1955 urging a no vote by AFTRA members on a proposed rule to "fine, censure, suspend or expel any member who fails to cooperate with the House Un-American Activities Committee."
Series V: Photographs and Recordings: contains images and audio related to Randolph's career, family life, and political activism. Randolph's photographs document his career and family life, and contain images of his military service in the 1940s, his children in the 1950s, his acting career, and several portraits. The audio recording in this series relate primarily to Randolph's career and activism and contain training materials, recordings of Randolph's voice work, and political speeches. There are also several recordings of African freedom songs from the 1970s. Most of these recordings are on magnetic reel to reel tapes, while a small portion of recordings are on cassette tapes. Other materials contained in this series include films negatives, slides, a VHS tape, and a CD of Randolph's memorial.
Separated Material
Photographs, audio- and video-tapes from the Randolph Papers have been separated to the Non-Print Department of the Tamiment Library.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Clippings (information artifacts); New York (N.Y.).; Blacklisting of entertainers.; Motion pictures and theater -- United States.; Scripts (documents); Tony Awards.; Los Angeles (Calif.); Legal documents.; Correspondence.; Actors -- Labor unions -- United States.; Actors -- United States.; Actresses -- United States.; Brand, Phoebe, 1907-2004; Cunningham, Sarah; Elder, Lonne; Jules, Dassin, 1911-2008.; Ensemble Studio Theatre; Philadelphia Drama Guild; Actors' Equity Association; American Federation of Television and Radio Artists; Robeson, Paul, 1898-1976; Screen Actors Guild; Ewen, Frederic, 1899-; Silvera, Frank, 1914-1970; Suhl, Yuri, 1908-1986; Piscator, Erwin, 1893-1966; Nelson, Steve, 1903-1993; Ntloedibe, Elias L.; Norman, Lloyd, 1914-; Randolph, Martha
- Series I: Correspondence, 1918-1999
  - Correspondence: Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Coalition for Economic Survival, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Lonne Elder, III re: Ceremonies in Dark Old Men (includes reviews for 1973 Philadelphia production), 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Frederic Ewen and Miriam Gideon Ewen, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Freedomways (includes Esther Jackson, Managing Editor), 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Robert Frey (includes manuscript of article by Frey about JR), 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Germany, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: In memory of Sarah, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: JR, 1935, 1941-1946, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: JR, 1961-1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: JR, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: JR, 1980, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: JR, 1994-1999 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: JR and SC, 1946-1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: JR to SC/SC to JR, 1953-1971 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Letter from JR's Father, Louis Cohen, to Cohen's brother, Jun 3, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Letters to SC (not from JR), 1940, 1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Norman Lloyd, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: Maudlyn "Mitzie" Martin employment with the Randolphs, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence: National Black Theatre Workshop, Barbara Ann Teer President, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence: New Theatre for Now Tour Cancellation, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence: New York Apartment, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence: Elias Ntloedibe from Kenya (mostly regarding song recordings), 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence: Elias Ntloedibe from Tanzania (includes press clippings and related materials), 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence: Erwin Piscator, Director of the Dramatic Workshop, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence: Andrea Primdahl, 1990s (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence: Randolph in Support of Lonne Elder, III and Elder's Essay, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence: Ralph Russell, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence: Frank Silvera, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence: Alan Simpson (United States Senator from Wyoming), 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence: Yuri Suhl, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence: Tony Award Congratulations, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence: Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB) (includes Steve Nelson and Moe Fishman), 1962, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence: James Whitmore, 1970S (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence: World War II, JR to SC, Jul 1941-Oct 1941 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence: World War II, SC to JR, Jul 1941-Aug 1941 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence: World War II, JR to SC, Nov 1941-Dec 1941 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence: World War II, JR and SCs Wedding, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence: World War II, letters to JR (not from SC but sent to her for safe keeping) from Jules Dassin, Frank Silvera, John Berry and Others, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence: World War II, JR to SC (Mrs. Randolph as of January 6th), Jan 1942-Aug 1942 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence: World War II, SC to JR (now known as Private Mortimer Lippman), Apr 1942-May 1942 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence: World War II, SC to JR, Jun 1942-Sep 1942 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence: World War II, JR to SC, Sep 1942-Dec 1942 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence: World War II, JR to SC, Jan 1943-Mar 1943, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence: World War II, SC to JR, Jan 1943-Mar 1943 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence: World War II, JR to SC, Apr 1943 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence: World War II, SC to JR, Apr 1943 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence: World War II, JR (a corporal as of June) to SC, May 1943-Sep 1943 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: World War II, SC to JR, Mar 1943-Jul 1943 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: World War II, JR to SC, Oct 1943-Dec 1943 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: World War II, SC to JR, Aug 1943-Dec 1943 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: World War II, letters to JR (not from SC, includes Jules Dassin and Frank Silvera), 1943 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: World War II, letters to SC (not from JR), 1943 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: World War II, JR to SC, Jan 1944-Jun 1944, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: World War II, SC to JR, Jan 1944-Jun 1944 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: World War II, JR to SC, Jul 1944-Dec 1944 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: World War II, SC to JR, Jul 1944-Dec 1944 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: World War II, letters to JR (not from SC), 1944 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: World War II, letters to SC (not from JR), 1944 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: World War II, JR to SC, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: World War II, SC to JR, Mar 1945-Apr 1945 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: World War II, SC to JR, May 1945-Dec 1945 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: World War II, letters to JR (not from SC), Jan 1945-Aug 1945 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: World War II, letters to SC (not from JR), Sep 1945-Dec 1945 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence and Related Materials: Martha Randolph, 1960-1997 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Series II: Subjects, 1940-1999
  - Actors' Equity Association (AEA), 1945-1974 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - AEA: "Broadway Blackout" clippings and notes, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - AEA: Council Election with JR Running by Petition, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - AEA: Ethnic Minorities Committee, 1962-1966, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - AEA: John Randolph Charges against Douglas Gregory, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - AEA Paul Robeson Award Committee, 1972-1998 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Agency Agreements: Sid Gold-Jack Fields, Abrams-Rubaloff, 1967, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Air Force Songs (sheet music), 1943 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - American Federation of Television and Radio Artists (AFTRA): General, 1962-1998 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - AFTRA: Los Angeles Local, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - AFTRA: Washington-Baltimore Local, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Announcer's General Operation Manual (with notes), 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Award: Advertising Club of New York, "Andy", 1968 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Award: Golden Laurel, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Biographical and Resume materials: JR, 1955-1995 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Biographical and Resume materials: SC, 1961-1972 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Blacklist: AFTRA Amendment against, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Blacklist: AFTRA Amendment in Support, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Blacklist: AFTRA Members Anti-AWARE, Inc. Resolution, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Blacklist: Anti-Subversive Committee, Cook County Council, the American Legion, May 1956 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Blacklist: Authors League of America, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Blacklist: Correspondence, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Blacklist: Letters to Actors' Equity, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Blacklist: Red Treason on Broadway by Myron Fagan, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Blacklist/House Committee on Un-American Activities (HUAC): Douglas Gregory Case Correspondence and Related Material, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Blacklist/ HUAC: Press Clippings and Related Material, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Blacklist/ HUAC: Press Clippings and Related Material, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Blacklist/ HUAC: Press Clippings and Related Material, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Blacklist/ HUAC: Press Clippings and Related Material, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Blacklist/ HUAC: Press Clippings and Related Material, 1961-1997 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Brotherhood of Artists: Mako, Chairman, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Class Day Skit written by Sarah Cunningham, Jun 1940 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Clippings: General, 1944, 1971, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Clippings: General, JR, 1994, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Clippings: General, SC, 1940, 1951, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Clippings: Political Issues, 1964-1996 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Commission for Human Rights, State of New York, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Committee for Employment of Negro Performers, 1962, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Czechoslovakia—Lessons for Us All (manuscript attributed to R.P.D.), 1968 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Diary [date book], 1940 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) File: John Randolph a/k/a Mortimer Lippman, a/k/a Emmanuel Cohen, Apr 11, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Funeral Records of Dorothy Lippman (JR's Mother), 1969 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Harlem: Proposal for an Independent Board of Education, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Honoring John Randolph Events, 1988, 1995-1997 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - House Committee on Un-American Activities (HUAC), undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - HUAC: Correspondence Received before and after Testifying, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - HUAC: Hate Groups and the Un-American Activities Committee, Pamphlet by David Wesley, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - HUAC: National Committee to Abolish, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - HUAC: Pamphlets and Related Materials Used in Preparation for Hearings, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - HUAC: Press Clippings and Related Material, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Issues: African-Americans (includes early materials on the "Negro performer"), 1953-1973 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Issues: Anti-War, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Issues: Freedom for Angela Davis, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Issues: Friendship Societies, 1983-1999 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Issues: General, undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Issues: National Committee against Repressive Legislation/Wilkinson v. FBI, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Issues: Resolution on the U.S. Office of Repertory Theatres/Sala Staw, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Issues: Rosenbergs (includes the National Committee to Reopen the Rosenberg Case), 1975-1988 (Box 3, Folder 53)